I'm not sure Israel is so crazy about
having uh America run Gaza
and uh it interferes to some degree with
their own plans
uh which are I think uh to occupy the
whole
of Gaza at least.
indirectly
and to have undisputed rights to claim
the offshore
uh natural gas deposits [music] which
are considerable apparently.
>> Hi, I'm John Kuryaku and welcome to Deep
Focus.
Before we get into the substance of uh
today's conversation, I want to ask you
the favor of uh subscribing to the
podcast, liking, sharing, commenting,
talk about it with your friends. It
means the world to us and it helps to
trigger that algorithm at YouTube that
makes it all so much better and uh and
gets word around.
I want to start by telling you a very
short personal story. Um I got out of
prison in 2015. I served 23 months after
blowing the whistle on the CIA's torture
program. Something I would do again
today if I had the opportunity.
Just after my release from prison, the
Greek government hired me to help them
write a new whistleblower protection law
and they flew me out to Athens to meet
with the Minister of Justice, the
Minister of State for Anti-Corruption,
and a half a dozen different
parliamentarians. But they did it on the
cheap. And the cheapest way to get me
out to Athens was to fly out through JFK
and to fly back to Washington through
Toronto. Toronto is in Canada.
Well, I went out to Greece. I worked
with the government and I flew back to
Toronto. When I got off the plane, or
maybe it would be more appropriate to
say as I was getting off the plane, two
members of the Royal Canadian Mounted
Police intercepted me just there at the
plane's door and grabbed me by both of
my arms.
I said, "Hey, what's up?" One of them
turned to me and said, "You are not
welcome in Canada." I said, "I'm not
entering Canada. I'm walking from one
plane to another so I can go home to
Washington. They didn't say anything
else to me the whole time, but they
physically pulled me by the arms through
the airport with people taking pictures
and video. It was all very embarrassing
and humiliating, which I think was
probably the point. And then they
physically walked me on to the
connecting plane to Washington. As I sat
down and put my seatelt on, they said,
"Don't come back to Canada."
That was my last experience with the
Canadians.
Well, today we're going to talk with a
bonafide American hero who we've had on
the show before. Professor Richard Faulk
has been everything I would want to be.
The United Nations special reperator on
uh human rights. a prominent voice in
support of human rights around the
world, but recently and specifically
human rights for Palestinians.
He's a a professor ameritus of law and
uh and the co-founder of a very
important organization that supports
human rights around the world. He also
had a recent and difficult
experience in Canada. Professor Faulk,
welcome back to the show. It's so good
to see you again.
>> Thank you so much, John. It's very
always good to be your guest.
>> Thank you. The pleasure. Believe me, the
pleasure is all mine. Professor,
I want to get into in in a few minutes
some of the the substantive issues
surrounding Gaza and the treatment of of
Palestinians there, especially
Palestinian civilians. But first, I want
to talk about what happened to you in
Canada. And it just so happened to take
place on your 95th birthday. [laughter]
Now you were you were accosted in Ottawa
at the airport. You had flown in from
California. Tell us what happened.
>> Uh well it's it's sort of a long uh tale
but an abbreviated version
is that um they took our passports.
I was with my wife uh who had also been
a UN special reporter.
Uh and we were led to a sort of a
holding area where we waited an half
hour
and then they told us to come follow
another
uh border security person and we went to
another room where uh we waited for
another half hour or so until uh border
security
agent came and uh said that he had the
obligation of uh questioning us so that
Canada could determine whether I was a
security threat [snorts]
uh to Canada. I'd never been flattered
in that way before.
Uh I
wondered what uh could have led to this
sudden elevation of my status to be a
security threat.
uh and
uh it eventually came out that from the
questions they posed that they were
interested in the uh event that I was
attending, which was a [snorts] a
tribunal organized by some young
Canadians,
uh to
uh it was called the Palestinian
Tribunal.
on Canadian responsibility
and it was devoted for the two days that
it lasted
to a variety of testimonies
from either survivors of the Gaza
genocide or
uh experts on aspects of the situation.
But uh the net effect was to create the
most um
uh devastating
inquiry into third party complicity.
Uh which of course other countries
are even more in need of illuminating
than Canada was. Starting with the US,
of course, that has been the most
stalwart of Israel's supporters
and has gone along even with this
uh
phony ceasefire that kills numerous uh
Palestinians
uh and yet is
still called a ceasefire. fire
there. I think there are over 200
violations of it in the 40 days it's
been in operation.
And really Israel is doing quietly and
without international
objection what it has been doing in a
much more accelerated form
uh before the ceasefire went into
effect. So it's a very peculiar
diplomacy that has that is emerging
and uh with a certain degree of UN
complicity at this stage.
not only the
uh countries that uh overtly support
Israel, but the countries that
uh indirectly do so through their way of
filtering the news in their uh media or
by um subtle ways of
uh indirectly ly assisting Israel by uh
encouraging
economic relations with their private
sector corporations
and other means of promoting national
economic and political interests.
>> Professor, let's talk for a second about
u these violations that we're seeing
taking place. Donald Trump said as
recently as as yesterday, we're
recording this on a Friday, uh, November
21st. He said as recently as yesterday,
that
thanks to him, there is peace in Gaza.
We all know that's not true. There's a
ceasefire kind of, sort of. Uh, but as
you noted, uh, truthfully, correctly,
the Israelis violate it constantly.
There have been hundreds of Palestinian
civil civilians killed just since the
announcement of the ceasefire.
Do you see that changing at all? Is
there any reason to be optimistic here
that the ceasefire will turn into some
sort of a peace?
Uh I I it's hard to be optimistic about
a uh plan that is another form of
uh 21st century o oppression.
It's a it's a there's no role for the US
or for
uh Europe to play in the governance of
Gaza. And yet this is not only a plan
for that kind of controlled governance,
but it puts the American president at
the head of a so-called board of peace
that is given the authority to
administer
uh the transition from whatever
accelerated genocide occurred
uh for the past two plus years
uh to some
stabilized condition under
uh western
supervision.
So it's it really carries forth out in
the open the allegation that the whole
uh Zionist undertaking
was a settler colonial
uh imposition
on a
uh society that had long been organized
around its
Arab Palestinian majority
and this idea of dis devising
what the future of Gaza is
on the part of
uh Europeans and North Americans
seems
historically out of touch with the
collapse of European colonialism.
It's a it's a kind of zombie colonialism
that occurs after
uh that takes its shape and uh uh
encounter with the native population
after the collapse of European
colonialism and other parts of the world
particularly Asia.
So it's a very uh strange uh kind of
phenomenon that's has
uh these original characteristics that
are not repeated uh in other
anti-colonial struggles.
Professor, I think just about every
non-Israeli observer of uh of the Gaza
conflict uh has come to the conclusion,
if they hadn't been there already, that
the only the only way out of this is
that there has to be an independent
Palestine. The Israelis of course have
utterly ruled this out. It will never
happen. Prime Minister Benjamin
Netanyahu said just about a week ago and
he has been saying it all of his life.
Um but it seems like there is no other
there is no other way to do this that
there has to be an independent Palestine
or maybe Palestine is in the West Bank
and Gaza has some sort of special
administrative status. I know the
Israeli press was uh writing briefly a
month or two ago about the idea that
perhaps
Israel would quote unquote own Gaza
while the Saudi government would
administer it on a day-to-day basis and
would invest in it so that they could
build a a port and an airport and an
electrical grid and water desalination
facilities and such. Do you see anything
like that happening? Is there any
stomach among the Israeli political
class to allow
at least some sort of administrative
assistance to Gaza or more broadly a
path to an independent Palestine?
uh at this point I mean one can't rule
out the improbable
because it's historically the improbable
sometimes occurred
and the most relevant example of that
would be uh the South African
turn away from a partate
rather than face this choice between
uh genocide
and continued resistance.
See, you come to a point
in in an effort to suppress
the native population
that it either s politically surreners,
which happened to the native peoples in
North America by and large and Australia
and New Zealand, or you go to the next
stage of repression.
which after a partate is genocide and uh
and echocidal
uh
secondary uh uh implications
as uh as in Gaza, which now is a virtual
wasteland
where the rain recent rains have flooded
some of the tent
communities
and they're forced to live in this uh
condition that would make what we call
homelessness
be seen as a kind of luxurious
lifestyle.
Uh uh and we we call that peace to
subject a population to uh that is
physically present in its own homeland
to be victimized in this extreme
continuing way where they where their
homes have been destroyed where their
access to adequate food and medicine has
been uh denied over a long period where
there's no uh safe drinking water
where electricity is very uh unstable
and unreliable
and all of these uh aspects
have been deliberately manipulated by
the IDF and the political leadership.
leadership of Israel to make the
suffering of the Palestinian people as
intense as possible.
uh and
that seems to make uh any kind of
strategic sense only if the Israeli
uh policy had is and has been one of
either
uh killing a large number of
Palestinians
or making conditions of uh uh of
remaining
so burdensome
that a lot of Palestinians will choose
the lesser of evils which is to become
uh refugees
[snorts] and to leave
and and th this is an ongoing pro
process. It has not ended with the
ceasefire.
The ceasefire has, as you earlier said,
diminished the drama of
uh 247
bombardment and uh devastation from the
air, but it hasn't eliminated
a a condition of acute suffering and
vulnerability
not only to uh Israeli uh militarism
but also to conditions that imperil
health particularly of young children
uh their health and development. So it's
really a spectacle of horror
that the eyes and ears of the world have
been exposed to
uh for many months. less so in the
countries supporting
uh Israel, the complicit
third party countries, but still
gradually enough of the imagery of
atrocity
has penetrated
uh western political consciousness that
one now finds growing tensions
between
uh the society
and the state over these issues.
where this the citizenry
has a greater moral sensitivity
uh than the elites running the country
uh that are thinking of very
uh selfish short-term interests
and not respecting
the their own pledge of never again
after the Nazi Holocaust. And one now
has to reinterpret that from a racist
uh perspective and and
say the slogan should be never again
against a white minority.
You raise a very important point here
that uh that frequently comes up in the
in the Arab press and that is uh what
appears to be
a a usually unspoken Israeli policy of
ethnic cleansing. And when I say ethnic
cleansing, I mean actively encouraging
Palestinians to get out. Uh, King um
Abdullah of Jordan and President Cece of
Egypt have both said that they will not
take Palestinian refugees, not because
their hearts aren't breaking for the
Palestinians, but because to do so would
further the Israelis policy of
ethnically cleansing Gaza, freeing it of
of any um any claim that Palestinians
may have to their ancestral land so they
can take it over and develop it and
settle it.
What's What's the solution to something
like this? You can't just allow people
to live in perpetuity in in rubble, the
rubble of their of their bombed and
destroyed homes. And if other countries
won't take them as refugees, can't take
them uh as refugees, then what's the
solution there?
uh well the uh most uh disturbing
uh I wouldn't call it a solution but the
most uh disturbing
uh scenario for the future
uh is is a
[snorts] continuation of the basic
structure of oppression and exploitation
with changing
the format to some superficial degree,
but from a Palestinian point of view,
still excluding them from any kind of
participation
in shaping their own future
and subjecting them to the ide to the
ideology of the Israelis that any
expression of resistance
uh is a form of terrorism
and that goes against the development of
international law in the course of the
antic-colonial struggles
which came step by step to the
conclusion that there is a human right
to resist
uh colonial
occupation
and colonial
uh policies that are exploitative.
and and that
uh uh Palestine is a a textbook example
of such a
uh structure of domination and explo
exploitation
which has been characterized
by the leading uh international human
rights
uh nos Amnesty International and human
rights touch as a definite form of
aparate
which is an international crime
developed in relation to South Africa
but not limited to the South African
situation.
the apartate convention
uh for the um pre uh pre prevention and
punishment of aparate was came into
force in 1972.
So it it goes back to the aparate
period,
but as I say, it is flexible enough to
be applied in the
given the facts of
uh Palestinian
uh victimization.
>> Professor, I was wondering if you might
comment a little bit on domestic Israeli
politics. Um, the reason I ask is that
we've seen what appears on the surface
of things to be a a a very strong
Israeli move to the political right to
the point where there are Israeli
ministers now like Idomar bin Gavir and
um
uh Smootri uh the minister of finance
who also is the security minister of the
West Bank.
These men have felony convictions for
anti-Palestinian hate crimes in their
past. Felony convictions in Israel. Even
by Israeli standards, their personal
positions were were too much for the law
to even be able to handle. Uh but there
are powerful ministers in the Netanyahu
government. Now, before October 7th,
Israel was experiencing demonstrations
the likes of which the country had never
seen before. and it looked like the
Netanyahu government was going to
collapse. Instead, it was able to
strengthen by rallying people against
the Palestinians.
Now, in the West Bank, it looks as
though the government may be losing
control, not to Palestinians, but to
settlers who have been attacking
Palestinians, killing them, burning
mosques, burning buildings, and the
government says that it's powerless to
stop them.
What are we seeing here in terms of
Israeli politics? Has the body politic
moved so far to the right that it's it's
out of control or uncontrollable?
Or is this a government policy where the
Israelis want us to think that they
can't control the settlers? or
is Netanyahu really more popular now
than he was before uh October 7th?
>> Well, you raise a series of very um
challenging issues
um that can't be authoritatively
uh answered because there's a lot of
uncertainty.
some of it deliberate uh
effort to
uh shift attention away from
uh what Israel has done to the
Palestinians.
partly a
way of keeping
the Israeli
public unified around an an
anti-Palestinian
political agenda.
We have to remember that when the uh
Netanyahu
coalition government
uh took control in Israel at the
beginning
of uh 2023,
but uh 10 months before the Hamas
attack,
it was already characterized even by the
mainstream western media as the most
extreme government in the history of
Israel.
And what made it extreme in my view was
its
uh only slightly disguised intention
to fulfill
the Zionist
uh vision of a
uh single
state, a a a one-state
outcome
with uh Israel.
presiding
and uh the uh ethnic
uh characteristics of a uh Jewish
supremist state being uh embodied in the
uh constitutional structure of the
country which it already is to a certain
degree as a result of the 2018
basic law which declared that only the
Jewish people have self-determination
within the boundaries of uh uh Israel
Palestine
that that incorporated the
occupied territories.
So what happened when uh this coalition
and the reason u that the ultraright got
into that uh leadership role was that uh
Netanyahu otherwise could not have uh re
reassumed
control over the governing process. In
other words, it was his
uh
need for
uh partners
that
in order to escape his uh fraud
accusations within Israel
and assume or reassume
uh control of the government that forced
him into this uh Fouian bargain.
uh with the uh ultra rightight. It
didn't depart so much from
uh his own uh agenda which was as you
suggest
always uh
always denied
uh the uh willingness
of Israel to allow a Palestinian a
genuine Palestinian state to come into
exist. existence
and what the Netanyahu coalition did
uh in addition to appointing these
religious extremists to very critical
uh cabinet positions and particularly
sensitive ones in relation to the
Palestinian
uh issues.
Uh
what they did was to greenlight
violence by the settlers
from day one. And they even provided uh
settlers with additional weaponry and
and played a a kind of double game. On
the one hand, as again you suggested,
claiming they had no control and on the
other hand facilitating
the outrages
that the settlers were perpetrating
which included leaving
uh notes on people's
uh on West Bank Palestinians cars which
read, "Leave or we will kill you.
And that I think represents the
uh core
uh core uh
uh passion
of uh ethnic cleansing.
It it it u tries to
portray ethnic cleansing as the
lesser
uh tragedy
and compares it in effect to genocide.
So that if a
uh subjugated people
uh fear
genocide,
they will uh choose the lesser option of
uh leaving.
And that's what Palestinians did in 1948
and again in 1967.
what the Palestinians
uh call by their Arabic uh by the Arabic
name Nakba
which translates as catastrophe.
[snorts]
Professor, help us understand too what
kind of conversations are taking place
among the royal families of Saudi
Arabia, Bahrain, the United Arab
Emirates, or even in countries like
Tunisia or Morocco or Sudan that have
relatively recently opened diplomatic
relations with Israel have not broken
them in light of uh of the the war in
Gaza. How do these how do these families
and governments justify continuing
diplomatic relations with Israel with
this treatment of Palestinians when you
would think they would be natural
defenders of the Palestinians?
Uh yes, it's a great uh disappointment I
think to the Palestinians
that they haven't received real support
from their uh Muslim brothers and
sisters.
>> [snorts]
>> Um, I think the explanation why they
haven't received support
is that the regimes in almost every one
of these
uh countries
is afraid of its own population
and needs uh the support of the US and
the West in order to feel politically
secure. cure.
And so on the one side it fears a
movement like the one associated with
Hamas
and uh Islamic Jihad
against in the taking the form of a
second Arab Spring
and the uh
desire on that their part
to please uh the US and
indirectly Israel.
They're dependent. Some of these
countries are dependent on Israel for
arms exports and a variety of
undisclosed
interactions,
including the uh unified
uh posture
uh against uh Iran and its present uh uh
political
uh makeup and theological
identity.
Israel and the uh leading Arab countries
uh oppo oppose and fear
uh the Iranian influence in the region.
And so
uh that creates a kind of uh
transactional bond
uh between Israel and its Arab
neighbors.
But but as you say, the cost of pursuing
such a pragmatic policy is to betray
their own uh ethical and
uh legal commitments to
a uh lawful and morally acceptable
uh policy.
Professor, you've been around for a long
time. As we said, your birthday was
recently and you turned 95 years old.
You've seen American politics over a a
great number of decades. We seem to have
the most pro-Israel administration in
history governing the country right now.
Uh, do you see this as a pendulum that
goes back and forth or is this the the
policy of the United States and it shall
remain the policy of the United States?
We've chosen our side and we're going to
seed leadership on the human rights
issue to anybody else who wants it. How
do you see this?
Well, I I think I differ uh somewhat
with your um initial po uh point of
departure that this is the most pro
pro-Israeli
government in history. I don't think on
the uh on the scale of real pro-Israeli
uh
commitments.
Uh the Biden uh presidency was not sub
substantially different than Trump. It
it was [snorts] more predictable.
And see, Trump is kind of unreliable and
pursuing a kind of narcissistic
uh geopolitics
which is very unstable from a Israeli
point of view. They don't uh they think
they can manipulate Trump and have
succeeded I think in the shaping of this
uh so-called peace plan.
But they if they were uh prudent they
would be
uh scared to place all their eggs in
that basket.
Uh Trump is uh very murial and if he
sees that he can get a better economic
deal with the Arab countries by
uh endorsing a Palestinian state or by
doing something that departs
from the uh position of unconditional
support. he's quite likely to do it in a
way that for instance Biden
uh wouldn't be likely to do. And one
change is in the the domestic scene. The
Zionist
lobbies
are less formidable
after this genocidal
uh experience. [snorts] and uh they
don't have the
uh at least silent acquiescence
of the broader society.
Their view
the relationship with Israel is no
longer viewed as a positive
aspect of American foreign policy.
American foreign policy
uh except in a condition of of some kind
of wartime
uh doesn't
um affect the voting behavior of most
Americans that are influenced by what
happens domestically
rather than
internationally.
And that
seems to be a continuing
characteristic.
Should
Americans have any reason to think that
u that this policy will change
regardless of who ends up in the White
House, regardless of which party
controls either of the two chambers of
Congress?
Is this just something that we have to
expect to tolerate or do you think
there's real a real possibility for
change in American policy in the Middle
East?
I think there's enough uncertainty
that now exists
that it's worth trying to exert
additional pressure to
uh make this change seem less
politically
costly
uh to uh members of Congress that I
think weren't genuinely so pro-Israeli
as they as much as they feared
the consequences for their own careers
of uh blatantly
opposing
what the uh pro-Israeli
uh lobby was uh seeking and demanding.
I think uh that lobby as I suggested has
much less leverage
than it used to have
and there's a stronger case
for
uh at least departing
from this position of
uh outright complicity
with what Israel is doing and whether uh
Trump in all his
uh
involvement with uh trying to take
credit for everything and put his name
attach his name to all kinds of uh
international and national
uh developments.
uh whether he
uh comes to
be disillusioned about
uh the prospects for his plan being
uh realized in in Israel and then what
happens after that happens. I'm not sure
Israel is so crazy about having uh
America run Gaza
and u it interferes to some degree with
their own plans
uh which are I think uh to occupy the
whole
of Gaza at least indirectly
and to have undisputed rights to claim
the offshore
uh natural gas deposits which are
considerable apparently
and didn't exist earlier when uh Israel
was more worried about the demography of
keeping Gaza than it was about the
political and economic consequences
of allowing allowing it to affiliate
with Jordan or possibly even Egypt or
become autonomous.
It was much readier for that because of
its demographic fears of a uh majority
Palestinian population
in uh Israel.
And it it on the one hand wanted to enex
uh the Palestinian territories.
On the other hand, it wanted to keep a
uh Jewish majority population
so it could have at least the u uh
appearance of being a political
democracy.
Professor, last question. I want to uh I
want to return to the Canada issue uh
for a moment. Were you able to get to
your conference? Were you able to speak
your peace? Did did they treat you with
respect? And and did you have any
problems leaving Canada?
Uh
it was very it was part of the
strangeness of the experience when they
finally uh did let us enter.
They then completely forgot about us and
the conference
and there was no problem. I never in all
my
uh years of traveling
had so little problem
uh entering uh the US as I did this time
where they absolutely didn't look at our
passports [snorts]
they it was very peculiar and Canada had
no interest in our when we departed
We uh they didn't uh
ask a single question where had we been
or what had we done
so it was there was something that
happened
that is a missing part in the puzzle
because I think that maybe see the
people who were arranging this tribunal
had some influence of their own and when
they heard we were having this trouble
they tried to put pressure on the prime
minister's office
uh to do something and I had as a former
student Lloyd Axeworthy who had been the
foreign minister
of Canada and much respected
public figure and they knew that I was
uh close to him. Uh and he uh he also
intervened
and proposes to write something about
the
uh situation which he considers also to
have been an outrage.
>> Well, I'm glad and I'm glad you uh you
got in and got out in one piece.
Professor
>> Professor Richard Faulk. Uh, thanks for
joining us. Professor Faulk is an
American professor ameritus of
international law. That's at Princeton
University. He's Eurommed Mediterranean
Human Rights Monitors, chairman of the
board of trustees. And he's the former
uh special reperator for human rights
with the United Nations. Thanks so much
for being with us. Great to see you
again.
>> Good. Thank you for having me, John. I
enjoyed our conversation.
>> Oh, I always enjoy them as well. Thanks
for taking the [music] time.
>> Good. It was well worth it.
>> All the best.